Guide to the George Chorpenning Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
George Chorpenning papers
1856-1903
WA MSS S-2767
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.88
(5 boxes) + 1 broadside folder
The papers consist of account books, financial records, legal records, correspondence, and maps that document George Chorpenning's operation of an overland mail route in western states during the 1850s, his subsequent petition to the United States government for reimbursement, and other business, including his interest in a quartz mine in Sparta, Oregon, owned by E. E. Clough. The papers include correspondence of Chorpenning's sons George and Frank relating to continued claims against the United States government, 1895-1903.
Chorpenning, George, 1820-1894
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Michael D. Heaston on the William Robertson Coe Fund No. 3, 2004.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
George Chorpenning
George Chorpenning (1820-1894) operated mail service in western states during the 1850s. Beginning in 1857, he petitioned the United States government for compensation and recovery of business losses, a claim that remained unresolved at his death in 1894.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of account books, financial records, legal records, correspondence, and maps that document George Chorpenning's operation of an overland mail route in western states during the 1850s, his subsequent petition to the United States government for reimbursement, and other business, including his interest in a quartz mine in Sparta, Oregon, owned by E. E. Clough. The papers include correspondence of Chorpenning's sons George and Frank relating to continued claims against the United States government, 1895-1903.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Account Books, 1856-1893. II. Business Records, 1856-1894. III. Correspondence, 1889-1903. IV. Other Papers, 1857-1891.
Letter carriers -- West (U.S.); Postal service -- West (U.S.); Quartz mines and mining -- Oregon; Sparta (Or.); United States -- Politics and government -- 1865-1900; Account books -- West (U.S.) -- 19th century; Maps (documents) -- West (U.S.) -- 19th century; Letter carriers -- West (U.S.) -- 19th century; Chorpenning, George, 1820-1894; Clough, E. E.; United States. Post Office Department; United States. Postmaster General
- Account Books, 1856-1893; Series I; 0.85; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1856-1889 March (Box 1, Folder 1-17)
  - 1889 July-1893, undated (Box 2, Folder 18-28)
- Business Records, 1856-1894; Series II; 0.42; (1 box)
  Organized by type of material.
  - Bills, 1874-1881 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Memoranda and other documents, 1858-1894 (Box 3, Folder 30-35)
  - Cancelled checks, 1856-1865 (Box 3, Folder 36-46)
- Correspondence, 1889-1903; Series III; 0.21; (1 box)
  - Unsorted correspondence, 1890-1903 (Box 4, Folder 47-51)
  - McDonald, John, 1888-1893 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - McManus, Henry, 1889 (Box 4, Folder 53)
- Other Papers, 1857-1891; Series IV; 0.42; (1 box) + 1 broadside folder
  Organized by type of material
  - Real estate documents, 1857-1861 (Box 5, Folder 54-59)
  - Photographs of George Chorpenning and family members, 1877-1891 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Prospectus, North Fork Consolidated Mining & Tunnel Company, 1881 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Printed reports relating to Chorpenning vs. The United States, 1857-1876 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Clippings and ephemera, undated (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Maps, undated (Box 6 (Broadside), Folder 64)
    Scope and Contents
    "Map showing the several mail routes through the Indian Country from 1850 to 1861, and Indian depredations committed upon mail trains"
    "Map of Oregon ditch property"
    United States Land Office, La Grande, Oregon, Survey maps
    Survey of "Township No. 77"